This XML file does not appear to have any style information associated with it. The document tree is shown below.
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:cc="http://cyber.law.harvard.edu/rss/creativeCommonsRssModule.html" version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>
<![CDATA[ Stories by Gabriel Ávila on Medium ]]>
</title>
<description>
<![CDATA[ Stories by Gabriel Ávila on Medium ]]>
</description>
<link>https://medium.com/@gabriel_avila?source=rss-e2a7c82d399b------2</link>
<image>
<url>https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/fit/c/150/150/1*6Ok2Qd3hA6tA4HzU7H4WFg.jpeg</url>
<title>Stories by Gabriel Ávila on Medium</title>
<link>https://medium.com/@gabriel_avila?source=rss-e2a7c82d399b------2</link>
</image>
<generator>Medium</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 08:01:23 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<atom:link href="https://medium.com/@gabriel_avila/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<webMaster>
<![CDATA[ yourfriends@medium.com ]]>
</webMaster>
<atom:link href="http://medium.superfeedr.com" rel="hub"/>
<item>
<title>
<![CDATA[ The right mindset for Software Engineers and a BIG invite ]]>
</title>
<link>https://medium.com/@gabriel_avila/the-right-mindset-for-software-engineers-and-a-big-invite-bd492f82fda5?source=rss-e2a7c82d399b------2</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/bd492f82fda5</guid>
<category>
<![CDATA[ coding ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ software-development ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ programming ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ mentorship ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ software-engineering ]]>
</category>
<dc:creator>
<![CDATA[ Gabriel Ávila ]]>
</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2023 04:02:54 GMT</pubDate>
<atom:updated>2023-07-28T04:02:54.513Z</atom:updated>
<content:encoded>
<![CDATA[ <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*vkyuNu5dqdVz5X0AxCy5tQ.jpeg" /></figure><p>Being a programmer is not an easy journey even having many resources available, most of them for free. Overconsumption of content and a lack of direction may bring the idea that you are disoriented. And there is a high chance that you truly are!</p><p>This feeling could reach any level in this career. We wrongly believe that only people that are transitioning to Software Engineering face this situation. False! I&#39;ve mentored a lot of Senior Engineers that felt <strong>stuck </strong>too!</p><p>This post aims to bring the right mindset for Software Engineers that I got from 13 years of experience.</p><h3>The growth mindset</h3><p>Learning hurts, there is no other way. If you truly want to learn, be ready to expose yourself to very frustrating situations.</p><p>Imagine that you want to learn how to play guitar. You try the first chords, your fingers are so rusted and you can barely touch the strings with the right strength. After 15 minutes of trying to play that easy song that you love… you can&#39;t handle the pain. You must stop!</p><p>In Software Engineering the same happens. It takes time to learn new concepts. You will suffer to make your first program alone. You will also suffer to understand Design Systems, SOLID, Clean Code, Design Patterns all these advanced concepts. Rookies or Seniors, we will suffer.</p><p>But the time will pass anyway. Should we get afraid of this? Of course not! We must understand that someday, somehow, we will have a huge spike in our learning curve as this chart shows.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*XN78EIvqWrkBSXo5QQDfiw.jpeg" /><figcaption>Spoiler: This chart repeats over and over again. The maturity phase doesn&#39;t last too long!</figcaption></figure><p>Embrace the pain and enjoy the journey! You are not alone.</p><h3>Practice! Even as a Senior…</h3><p>Technology changes so fast! As Software Engineers we want to serve our Businesses with the best tools ever. But what happens if you get rusty? What happens if there are betters tools in the market that would save time and you have no idea? Well, I witnessed great people succumbing to laziness and comfort.</p><blockquote>I still remember… They felt so secure, the tech market was an oasis. Everywhere you look there are Tech Recruiters begging for attention. LinkedIn inboxes? Full of offers… C&#39;mon, we are kings! Then, the layoffs started, people got scared and the lazier team workers were <strong>fired</strong>.</blockquote><p>Getting back from this situation is hard. Who wants a guitar player in your band that is rusty and doesn&#39;t know the new trends? No one!</p><p>Programmers, please listen to me. Watch tutorials and code. Get a bootcamp and then code. Get a coffee, then code. Go to the bathroom, then code. Ask for reviews, then code again. Get an idea, then code. Repeat it without &quot;a break&quot;.</p><p>Chefs that know all recipes but don’t cook are worthless. Same for Software Engineers that don’t practice and don’t know the foundations to build things from scratch.</p><h3>Soft skills are (g)old</h3><p>Invest in soft skills. I know they look outdated! You may think: “We live in a digital world. In a world of emojis! Why should I learn to be a better communicator?”</p><p>I’ve interviewed and mentored probably more than one hundred people and trust me, programmers that know how to get their job done with great communication, accountability, respect, and quality are gold. I want them on my team at all costs.</p><h3>Dream &amp; Believe</h3><p>My daughters love to tell stories. They create those stories where they have powers and can fight against wolves and lions. Unfortunately, I feel that we lost this power of <strong>dreaming</strong>. Do you remember that question: “What do you want to be when you grow up?” We were used to dreaming.</p><p>Most engineers, especially seniors, lost their dreams somewhere on the road. I have my theories, but I still don’t have the courage to try a final answer for this phenomenon.</p><p>Even though, I’d love to invite you to dream again. Dream high! Write your dreams in a paper, in Google Docs, and share it with your loved ones. Then… execute it.</p><p>It will take time, but don’t stop, don’t quit. One of the biggest differences between successful people and unsuccessful people is that they don’t stop. Remember the learning curve chart… it takes time, maybe years, maybe decades.</p><h3>The BIG invite</h3><p>Finally, I want to invite you to my <strong>free mentorship</strong>. It took a long time in my career to get a mentor and it was a big game changer. This mentorship will happen every Monday, 8 pm EST.</p><p>The idea is simple, let&#39;s build a community! Let&#39;s sit down together, share experiences, stories, obstacles, talk about interviews, review code, pair programming, and so much more. Someday you could even be the leader of the meeting, why not? Let&#39;s help each other in this chaotic world.</p><p>Helping each other is like being a conductor. Some people are like lamps that have all the potential within but there is no electricity passing through them. They just need a little help to shine…</p><p>I&#39;ve been there. I also felt stuck, but I can help you. Just send me a message on my LinkedIn and I will share more information.</p><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gabriel-avila/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/gabriel-avila/</a></p><p>Don&#39;t miss this opportunity! I don&#39;t know for how long I will keep this mentorship. The time is <strong>now!</strong></p><p>If this is not interesting to you, help some lamps out there. Please share this post and this BIG invite. I count on you! Let&#39;s shine💡</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=bd492f82fda5" width="1" height="1" alt=""> ]]>
</content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>
<![CDATA[ Which are the best values that any Software Engineer should have? ]]>
</title>
<link>https://medium.com/@gabriel_avila/which-are-the-best-values-that-any-software-engineer-should-have-12a312a9a411?source=rss-e2a7c82d399b------2</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/12a312a9a411</guid>
<category>
<![CDATA[ values ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ software-engineering ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ programming ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ coding ]]>
</category>
<dc:creator>
<![CDATA[ Gabriel Ávila ]]>
</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 16:39:06 GMT</pubDate>
<atom:updated>2022-05-12T16:39:06.899Z</atom:updated>
<content:encoded>
<![CDATA[ <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*PVh-57wceNkz2t63CrNd2w.jpeg" /></figure><p>Values and fundamentals are better than just technical skills. Technical content will change and will be improved. The code that we write today is very different than decades ago. Although, values may last forever.</p><p>After many years working in this area and with different people around the world, I strongly believe that the best values that you could have as a Software Engineer are the following.</p><h3>Quality First</h3><p>You always try to write the best code. Going well is going faster!</p><h3>Adaptability</h3><p>You are not attached to a framework, specific language, or just one project. You easily adapt to new environments.</p><h3>Communication</h3><p>You have clear and objective written and verbal communication, especially in your code.</p><h3>Growth mindset</h3><p>You should know which are the next steps to improve as a Software Engineer and you are always learning.</p><h3>Testability</h3><p>You don’t trust in your ability to test all things. You automate this process.</p><h3>Humanity</h3><p>You treat others with respect and humanity.</p><h3>Mentoring</h3><p>You can teach others. When you teach, you learn more.</p><h3>Conclusion</h3><p>The main idea of this post is to be simple, just to help you to remind which values you should be aware of as a Software Engineer and get to the next level.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=12a312a9a411" width="1" height="1" alt=""> ]]>
</content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>
<![CDATA[ Design Patterns with TypeScript: Singleton ]]>
</title>
<link>https://medium.com/@gabriel_avila/design-patterns-with-typescript-singleton-c247f00b7350?source=rss-e2a7c82d399b------2</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/c247f00b7350</guid>
<category>
<![CDATA[ typescript ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ software-engineering ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ design-patterns ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ clean-code ]]>
</category>
<dc:creator>
<![CDATA[ Gabriel Ávila ]]>
</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 11:23:07 GMT</pubDate>
<atom:updated>2021-10-22T11:23:07.686Z</atom:updated>
<content:encoded>
<![CDATA[ <figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*ScaOx8Wu9ivDMyILeJVKBQ.jpeg" /></figure><p>I really want to explain Design Patterns in my own words. As Albert Einstein said:</p><blockquote><em>If you cannot explain it simply, you don’t understand it well enough. — Albert Einstein</em></blockquote><p>So, let’s try to explain Design Patterns simply and in my own words with some examples in Typescript, a coding language that I’m working on more nowadays.</p><p>Let’s see this Design Pattern called <strong>Singleton</strong>. I know that this Design Pattern could be the simplest one, but still is important to understand its foundations to be able to use it properly.</p><p>When you understand how the tool works, you have the ability to not be limited by just one point of view or just one use case, you can see the whole landscape and maybe use this tool in more cases.</p><h3>Why Design Patterns?</h3><p>Software engineering is a hard field with a lot of problems. Those architectural problems probably were already solved by someone and there is a guide to follow which we call “Design Patterns”.</p><p>The point is: don’t try to recreate a solution that already exists. Be smart! Learn with the previous “generations” and create something better, based on previous knowledge, for the next generations. That’s how Software Engineering will evolve.</p><blockquote><em>Learn from previous solutions, create better systems, leave a bigger legacy for the next Software Engineers.</em></blockquote><p>We should stand on the giant’s shoulders! Check out my Medium profile to see all other Design Patterns articles that I’ve written.</p><h3>The problem</h3><p>We have an integration app that should sync two systems: Hubspot and Zoho. We are going to sync only the <em>Contacts</em> object from scratch. Both systems should have the same contacts list.</p><p>This app is going to sync both systems every 30 seconds and that’s a client’s requirement. On each execution, only the new items will be brought from both systems.</p><p>However, what happens if we have a big payload on execution #1 and it takes 40 seconds to be finished, and then, execution #2 already started 10 seconds ago? Can you see this snowball effect? 😅</p><p>Well, in this case, execution #1 and execution #2 will basically see the same state from both systems, which means we might have duplicated creation requests. Also, Hubspot and Zoho do not have unique keys, so we will see duplicated objects if we make the POST request twice.</p><p>That’s a big problem! We don’t want to see duplicated objects. How can we solve that?</p><h3>Singleton</h3><p>Singletons ensure that exists only one instance for that class. Singletons have this workflow:</p><ul><li>Do we already have an instance built?</li><li>No: Build it</li><li>Yes: Return the built instance previously</li></ul><p>Why is that important? It’s important because it ensures we have only one instance for that class and that could help us on:</p><ul><li>Reduce the amount of memory usage</li><li>Create one global point on the entire system, i.e. we have the same state on the entire system</li></ul><p>That’s why Singleton is most used to dealing with database connections. It’s preferable to have as few connections as possible and Singleton does that pretty well.</p><p>But that does not mean that Singletons can only be used for Database Connections. We could use them to store params, configurations, definitions, service locators, or items that are useful on different parts of your app.</p><h3>Applying the Singleton Pattern</h3><p>To apply the Singleton Design Pattern we should:</p><ul><li>Create the instance static attribute which will be null or the built object</li><li>Turn the constructor private. With that, no one can create new objects of this class</li><li>Create a static method that will work as the constructor</li></ul><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/568/1*4yQhvChJMrk-Vg3VpRZx3w.png" /><figcaption>Example of Singleton’s structure</figcaption></figure><h3>CreateRequestsStore</h3><p>Getting back to our problem, to avoid duplicated requests we can create the <em>CreateRequestsStore, </em>which will be a Singleton to store the hashes of the requests in process<em>.</em></p><p>Basically, the idea here is:</p><ul><li>Integration app runs</li><li>It brings the new items from both systems (Hubspot and Zoho)</li><li>It goes on each new object to be created</li><li>It creates a hash of the object to be created</li><li>It checks if this hash already exists on the <em>CreateRequestsStorage</em> Singleton</li><li>If it does, skip the request to avoid duplicated requests</li><li>If it does not, make the request</li><li>When the request is finished, schedule execution in 2 minutes to remove this hash from <em>CreateRequestsStorage </em>through <em>setTimeout </em>(we really want to ensure that we won’t have duplicated data, 2 minutes sounds good)</li></ul><p>With that Singleton, we can avoid duplicated requests in run time. The <em>CreateRequestStore</em> class will look like this:</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/588/1*J_1Tytl6TmmZ8oSpn_sTmw.png" /></figure><p>Explaining the public methods, we have:</p><ul><li><em>getOrBuild()</em><strong><em>: </em></strong>to get or build the instance</li><li><em>addRequest()</em>: to add a new request object into the store. It returns the built hash</li><li><em>isRequestInProcess()</em>: to verify if the request object is in process</li><li><em>removeRequestByHash()</em>: to remove the hash from requests in the process list</li></ul><h3>SyncHubspotZoho</h3><p>Now the <em>SyncHubspotZoho</em> just needs to use the <em>CreateRequestsStore </em>and it should work as we agreed above. It will look like this:</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/924/1*fbhcpBW8786muPfdafnMUg.png" /></figure><p>This class is getting all the new contacts from both systems and creating them on each other (Hubspot to Zoho; Zoho to Hubspot) only when the object to be created does not exist on <em>CreateRequestsStore. </em>The hash of the object is removed 2 minutes later its creation.</p><p>Since the sync will happen every 30 seconds and we might have big payloads, in this case, the execution could delay and the next execution would start before the previous one finishes. This snowball effect might generate duplicated creation requests, but this solution will totally avoid this undesired behavior.</p><p>P.S.: This code above is not concerned about retrying policies, errors, or anything else. The focus here is a real usage of Singleton.</p><h3>Use Singleton wisely</h3><p>There are tons of articles saying that Singletons violate the Single Responsibility Principle. Since any part of the system can mutate its state, it could cause bugs. Also, bad programmers could use the Singleton to store anything.</p><p>I don’t completely agree with them. I believe that using Singleton pretentiously might cause bugs and it will violate SRP.</p><p>Here where I work, we had to create a Singleton to store some definitions to be used in the entire app. It worked great without causing bugs or bringing confusion to our system.</p><p>Although I agree that most lazy developers would use Singleton in a bad way, without thinking about the pros and cons, just using it pretentiously. So, to make your Singleton not violate the SRP:</p><ul><li><strong>Do only one thing in your Singleton</strong>.</li></ul><p>In this example, we just use this Single as a store for hashes. That’s it!</p><p>With that, you can avoid coupling too many things in your Singleton. Be wise! Design Patterns should be the solution, not the problem.</p><h3>Conclusion</h3><p>Now we can understand a little bit more of this simple and kind of underrated Design Pattern that could be so useful on the right hands.</p><p>After my studies, I believe that Singletons are great when you have to create a unique object:</p><ul><li>Seeking to reduce the amount of memory usage or resources, like Database Connections</li><li>Or it should be available on the entire system like Definitions, Configuration, Service Locators, i.e. simple stores.</li></ul><p>I hope that this article can turn you into a great developer that will use this Design Pattern wisely.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=c247f00b7350" width="1" height="1" alt=""> ]]>
</content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>
<![CDATA[ Design Patterns with Typescript — Strategy ]]>
</title>
<link>https://medium.com/@gabriel_avila/design-patterns-with-typescript-strategy-35007cbcd57a?source=rss-e2a7c82d399b------2</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/35007cbcd57a</guid>
<category>
<![CDATA[ typescript ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ clean-architecture ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ design-patterns ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ clean-code ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ javascript ]]>
</category>
<dc:creator>
<![CDATA[ Gabriel Ávila ]]>
</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 16:01:03 GMT</pubDate>
<atom:updated>2021-08-30T16:00:15.074Z</atom:updated>
<content:encoded>
<![CDATA[ <h3>Design Patterns with Typescript: Strategy</h3><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1000/0*6OHeXxmXeTI3tuTX" /></figure><p>I really want to explain Design Patterns in my own words. As Albert Einstein said:</p><blockquote>If you cannot explain it simply, you don’t understand it well enough. — Albert Einstein</blockquote><p>So, let’s try to explain Design Patterns simply and in my own words with some examples in Typescript, a coding language that I’m working on more nowadays.</p><p>Let’s see this Design Pattern called <strong>Strategy</strong>.</p><h3>Why Design Patterns?</h3><p>Software engineering is a hard field with a lot of problems. Those architectural problems probably were already solved by someone and there is a guide to follow which we call “Design Patterns”.</p><p>The point is: don’t try to recreate a solution that already exists. Be smart! Learn with the previous “generations” and create something better, based on previous knowledge, for the next generations. That’s how Software Engineering will evolve.</p><blockquote>Learn from previous solutions, create better systems, leave a bigger legacy for the next Software Engineers.</blockquote><p>We should stand on the giant’s shoulders!</p><h3>The problem</h3><p>Let’s imagine that your application is responsible to process payments. The goal of processing a payment is pretty simple, we should charge the client. However, there are some ways to do that like:</p><ul><li>Credit Card</li><li>Debit Card</li><li>Billet</li><li>Automatic Charge in your bank account (like GoCardless)</li><li>Bitcoin</li><li>And it goes on…</li></ul><p>So, we have different ways to charge a client. In that case, we have algorithms that do the same thing in different ways. In a part of their code, they are different, but their goal is the same, which is to <strong>charge the client</strong>.</p><p>How can we solve this? Well, we could have one simple class that will process the payment with different methods. But that would bring a lot of responsibilities for the same class, which doesn’t follow the Single Responsibility Principle (SRP) or even Open Closed Principle (OCP), since we should change the Payment class for each new way to charge the client.</p><p>Therefore, how to solve this elegantly?</p><h3>Strategy</h3><p>The way we can solve this is using the Strategy Design Pattern, which is a behavioral design pattern. This class will receive the “strategy” to achieve this objective. So, that fits so well in our example. We want to charge clients in different ways.</p><p>To apply the strategy pattern we are going to have:</p><ul><li>One interface structuring the way the strategies must work</li><li>One strategy class, which will call this specific method from the given strategy</li><li>Multiple classes to do the same thing in such a different way</li></ul><p>Let’s dive deeper into the TypeScript code.</p><h3>Types and Interfaces</h3><p>Here we are going to define the structure that the strategies should follow. We consider a strategy the class that will do the same thing differently. So, this interface will be the contract between all strategies:</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/297/1*Yqhl1rxPIHJj2HL-XfG13g.png" /></figure><p>Here we have a Payment type and the interface has just one single method: <strong>charge()</strong>, which should return a Payment.</p><p>That’s easy! Let’s check the different ways to charge a client and how they must follow this interface.</p><h3>Charging with Debit card and Credit card</h3><p>Here we should define the classes that will do the same thing in different ways. The same thing: charge the client. The different ways: one will do it by a credit card, the other one will do it by a debit card.</p><p>They will look like this:</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/547/1*hYXdKGA7UXzqFIOm9Znxzg.png" /></figure><p>Each one implements the PaymentMethod interface, that’s why they both should have the <strong>charge()</strong> method. There are a lot of benefits by doing this:</p><ul><li>Each class has its own business rules to do the same thing (Separation of Concerns).</li><li>Each class has its own responsibility (Single Responsibility Principle).</li><li>It’s easy to extend. If there’s another way to charge the client, we just need to create a new class implementing the PaymentMethod interface. That totally follows Open Closed Principe (OCP).</li></ul><p>As you can see, this is an elegant way to split the responsibilities. However, how are they going to work? That’s why we are going to see the next class: the PaymentStrategy.</p><h3>PaymentStrategy</h3><p>This is going to be a class where we can set up the strategy that we are going to use at that moment. We have different ways to do the same thing, but which one should we use? The strategy receives it!</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/436/1*4RUAOBCV7RzTzopH1Vpfyw.png" /></figure><p>So now we are totally able to set up the strategy that we want to use:</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/642/1*dEJg0nkfWGbHOdeY_yWSSA.png" /></figure><p>What if we want to use the debit card strategy? That’s easy!</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/639/1*BssmzUMV_tmuUrytvuwHew.png" /></figure><h3>Conclusion</h3><p>Now we know an elegant solution to do the same thing in different ways. And that’s called: Strategy Design Pattern.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=35007cbcd57a" width="1" height="1" alt=""> ]]>
</content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>
<![CDATA[ Recording a List of Seeds as Migrations do on Sequelize ]]>
</title>
<link>https://medium.com/@gabriel_avila/recording-a-list-of-seeds-as-migrations-do-on-sequelize-945ce1e18415?source=rss-e2a7c82d399b------2</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/945ce1e18415</guid>
<category>
<![CDATA[ node-js-tutorial ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ node ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ sequelize ]]>
</category>
<dc:creator>
<![CDATA[ Gabriel Ávila ]]>
</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 10:39:16 GMT</pubDate>
<atom:updated>2021-03-12T10:39:16.151Z</atom:updated>
<content:encoded>
<![CDATA[ <p>This post will be very short, it’s more like a reminder to myself. So often I need to store a list of seeds executed as migrations do on Sequelize. It’s easy to configure CI/CD to run all seeds since our seeds have the domain data.</p><p>However, when I need it for bigger projects, I often forget how to do it. So, here we go:</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/309/1*vf-2mpIcV-xdqJxDOrq-eQ.png" /></figure><p>That’s it! We just need to set the <strong>seederStorage</strong> attribute and we are fine!</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/320/0*r563JpSDiGU1P9IY.gif" /></figure><p>It’s important to remember that we have the following options:</p><ul><li>sequelize: Where Sequelize will store the executed seeds on the database (also, you can set a table name, different from the default name “SequelizeData”)</li><li>json: It will store the executed seeds in a JSON file</li><li>none: It will not save the executed seeds</li></ul><p>I really don’t know why that’s not the default behavior, but… never mind! I already have a post to remember me lol.</p><p>You can read more about it on <a href="https://sequelize.org/master/manual/migrations.html#seed-storage">Sequelize Documentation — Seed Storage Section</a></p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=945ce1e18415" width="1" height="1" alt=""> ]]>
</content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>
<![CDATA[ The Basics of Security Concepts to Protect Your Web Service ]]>
</title>
<link>https://medium.com/@gabriel_avila/the-basics-of-security-concepts-to-protect-your-web-service-36b11c3af36f?source=rss-e2a7c82d399b------2</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/36b11c3af36f</guid>
<category>
<![CDATA[ nodejs ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ programming ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ security ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ software-engineering ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ javascript ]]>
</category>
<dc:creator>
<![CDATA[ Gabriel Ávila ]]>
</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 22:34:33 GMT</pubDate>
<atom:updated>2020-07-28T22:34:33.402Z</atom:updated>
<content:encoded>
<![CDATA[ <p>You can see this post on <a href="https://trio.dev/blog/web-service-security">Trio’s blog</a> as well.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*gXvejlEKW16PLsac.jpg" /></figure><h3>Introduction</h3><p>Nowadays,<a href="https://www.kdnuggets.com/2019/02/top-10-technology-trends-2019.html"> “security” is a buzzword</a>. In a time where data is extremely important to protect. Forget about the gold or even cryptocurrencies, for a moment. The growth of interest in our data, and consequently its theft, is driven largely by Data Science, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, and even BI, and experienced with cyberattacks. With so much personal information about our customers, we must think more about security and how to store this new type of “gold”.</p><p>Data policies like <a href="https://gdpr.eu/">GPDR</a> (General Data Protection Regulation) aim to protect user’s personal data within any system that they are using. If their information is shared with another company, etc, it must be done with their consent. We can even see a clause that stipulates that companies must notify users of a data breach within 72 hours of discovering the problem. In this regulation, the penalties could reach<a href="https://gdpr.eu/fines/"> €20 million or 4% of annual global turnover.</a></p><p>Data protection is crucial and there is no better way to illustrate this than the <a href="https://www.equifax.com/personal/">Equifax</a> data breach, which impacted the personal information of approximately 147 million people in September of 2017. Equifax is one of the three largest consumer credit reporting agencies in the US and suffered a huge data breach all because of a little issue that could have been easily fixed. More on that in a bit. In the wake of their scandal,<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2019/07/22/equifax-fine-ftc/"> Equifax will have to pay up to $700 million in fines</a> as part of a settlement with federal authorities over this data breach.</p><p>Another company discovered a hacker who had stolen almost $250K in products without paying for them. This company just discovered the fraud in the next financial cycle (one month later), where they could see money missing. Unfortunately, they decided to invest in security only right after this situation. I’m telling you these stories to illustrate the gravity of these situations to you because any data breach could affect your company in ways you don’t ever want.</p><p>In this post, we will go through the basics of security to protect your web application or service. These concepts could be applied in any web service besides languages, but my examples will be more focused on Javascript (<a href="https://nodejs.org/en/">Node.JS)</a> with<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/express"> Express</a> and<a href="https://sequelize.org/"> Sequelize ORM</a>.</p><h3>1. Don’t trust in your client</h3><p>There is no way of knowing whether our users have good intentions or not so, we can’t trust any data inputted by our customer. This means that we need to check every input. We can do it with a blacklist or a whitelist.</p><p>In a blacklist, we have bad inputs that are deemed unacceptable as user inputs. In a whitelist, we have inputs that we allow to exist. Let’s take a look at an example.</p><p>We know that eval() is a function that executes strings as commands in Javascript. Surely, a user with good intentions wouldn’t use this kind of content as an email. So, we will replace every eval() to be empty.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/510/0*v-OkAs_yO9TInSlZ" /></figure><p>This can be helpful, however with every new threat we have to check our code and clean it up. So for this stage, whitelists are more reliable than blacklists. We have awesome libraries that help us to create quick whitelists checks in our routes, for example, <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@hapi/joi">Hapi/JOI</a>. Look at this example, where we check the inputs for user authentication:</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/530/0*wkjWRbWDfm8Hcisb" /></figure><p>This example above is awesome because this library will guarantee us two things:</p><ol><li>A good whitelist with good standards. If the input doesn’t fit with our standards, the <em>new Error() </em>will be triggered.</li><li>Protection against Parameter Injection, which means that the hacker tries to send more parameters to our routes. If there exists any different parameter besides email and password, the <em>new Error() </em>will be triggered;</li></ol><p>About Parameter Injection, I once witnessed a large company get hacked with this technique by an ethical hacker. These were his steps:</p><ul><li>He found the profile page;</li><li>He saw that the profile page was using the <em>PATCH</em> request, i.e. the application was sending a request to update the profile data;</li><li>He tried to add some new parameters on this request and one of them was <em>isAdmin: true;</em></li><li>His regular user turned into an admin user.</li></ul><p>In our example, the only parameters allowed are email and password, and they must adhere to our standards. Don’t forget to use whitelists, they’re very helpful! They can help against Parameter Injection and XSS.</p><h3>2. Use bind-params in your SQL statements</h3><p>You’ve probably heard about SQL Injections, and how powerful they can be. If you haven’t heard about them then I suggest you read about them. In addition, check<a href="https://owasp.org/www-project-top-ten/"> OWASP Top Ten Attacks</a>. But essentially, an attacker tries to change the queries that the system makes and gets access to the entire database.</p><p>I will never forget the day I was talking about SQL Injection breach with one of my co-workers. He challenged me to access a system that he made for his friend through a SQL Injection attack. This system didn’t use the bind params, so I got the admin user and I put in the password field a well-known SQL Injection command to bypass the password for any user, and voilá! I got admin access. Now, thinking about this story, I fell that I should have bet a beer with him.</p><p>The most simple solution is to use bind params. Bind params change the values inside of the database making it impossible to break the query and change to another one. Nowadays, most of the ORMs use bind params as default but pay attention to not make a custom query and execute it without bind params. For example, in Node.JS + Sequelize, if we want to use a custom query, we could do something like:</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*ber0jovpWH-KkrMb" /></figure><p>The image above shows two methods, the first method is an example with a custom query without bind params and the second is one with a custom query using bind params. You might’ve guessed right, the second method is the better one. If you have to use custom queries, then please, don’t forget to use the bind params. Also, ensure that your ORM uses them too. I know Sequelize does by watching the logs, and I know the most famous ORMs are using them, but if you’re the kind of person that loves to try new technologies and libraries, that’s a good point to start your decision if that ORM is good or not.</p><p>Therefore, don’t use any kind of query without bind params. SQL Injection is considered one of the most famous of the top ten attacks on web applications, and it was discovered in the ’90s. So, it shows how neglected the most developers and engineers have been. I still don’t know why we don’t teach the developers to use bind params since the first class to connect on the database and make queries.</p><h3>3. Don’t expose sensitive data</h3><p>How often does your web service handle sensitive data? If you never asked yourself this question, probably your web service exposes more sensitive data than you think.</p><p>The first step is to apply an SSL/TLS certificate on our web service and use it as the default connection. We can’t accept HTTP connections anymore for systems that use our personal information! This certificate ensures that we have an encrypted connection between servers and customers, which almost mitigates “data sniffing” from a third party (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man-in-the-middle_attack">Man in the Middle attack</a>).</p><p>Next, ask yourself: how could we help hackers to access our information? Showing system errors to them! Errors can sometimes display a lot of sensitive information such as the database system, table names, field names, constraint names, the language (Javascript, Java, Python, etc) and sometimes we can even see hosting information and passwords. When that happens, it gives to hackers a good guide to exploring the known security breaches for the technology, systems, frameworks, and language that your web service works with.</p><p>I can’t stress this one point enough: <strong>do not show errors to users</strong>. We need to intercept them and send them to programs like<a href="https://rollbar.com/"> Rollbar</a> or<a href="https://sentry.io/welcome/"> Sentry</a>. These programs have great support for many languages not to mention it’s pretty simple to configure your exceptions to show a default message to the user and send the system error to those tracker programs.</p><p>In the end, it’s best to show to user a default error message or a described user-friendly error message (it depends on your web service and your business rules) instead of showing the whole system error. Do you don’t know what could be your default error message? Just try: “Internal Server Error”. It’s so much better and reliable when a system shows it rather than the whole system error.</p><h3>4. Check your third-party libraries</h3><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2019/07/22/equifax-fine-ftc/">Equifax will pay up to $700 million in fines</a>. Could you imagine your company being responsible for a huge data breach like that? So, what happened on Equifax? Well, it’s not a complicated story to tell.</p><p>Equifax had a system that used Apache Struts. Two months before the attack, Apache Struts had announced a new patch to fix a specific vulnerability. Two months later, the hacker was exploiting this vulnerability which means that<a href="https://www.wired.com/story/equifax-breach-no-excuse/"> Equifax didn’t update their systems</a>.</p><p>This was the result:</p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2Fe6fIuRqu6wc%3Ffeature%3Doembed&amp;display_name=YouTube&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3De6fIuRqu6wc&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2Fe6fIuRqu6wc%2Fhqdefault.jpg&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=youtube" width="854" height="480" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/3938d50d1e323977098d11b406e6dd53/href">https://medium.com/media/3938d50d1e323977098d11b406e6dd53/href</a></iframe><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2FV38eMXbK7gg%3Ffeature%3Doembed&amp;display_name=YouTube&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DV38eMXbK7gg&amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2FV38eMXbK7gg%2Fhqdefault.jpg&amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=youtube" width="854" height="480" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/ce5dd7eb035b0056dcd77e0edc9e7f64/href">https://medium.com/media/ce5dd7eb035b0056dcd77e0edc9e7f64/href</a></iframe><p>To prevent this kind of problem, we have to look at our third-party libraries. Nowadays, it’s almost impossible to create any application without using any third-party library or framework. But one has to ask, who made that library? How well managed is it?. We are human beings and we make mistakes. Therefore, as a developer, it is your responsibility to manage the integrations you use. This means to assess their risks, and understand the potential effects it can have on your system, and stay up to date on any updates.</p><p>There’s a fantastic tool called<a href="https://snyk.io/"> Snyk</a>, which keeps developers vigilant to failures, vulnerabilities, and problems with your integrations. Snyk has a huge database with a lot of contributors and when they find a new vulnerability, they warn all their customers that have Snyk set in their applications. Most of the time they fix the new vulnerabilities automatically with one command that you need to run. Also, Snyk warns you via your email.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/630/0*k8i8rrv1L0oF9f-f" /></figure><p>Snyk is truly incredible! I, personally, love how companies are working hard to give significant value, especially when it comes to security. That’s why they got<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2020/01/21/snyk-snags-150m-investment-as-its-valuation-surpasses-1b/"> more than $1B of valuation</a>. They also have free plans and priced plans. Currently, I use the free plan for my personal projects and they support a lot of languages and package managers.</p><h3>5. Set some limits for the user</h3><p>I’m very enthusiastic about cryptocurrencies and Bitcoin, and I talk more about the <a href="https://trio.dev/blog/beyond-bitcoin-5-industries-successfully-applying-blockchain-technology-69675">usage of blockchain on the Trio’s blog</a>. I remember witnessing the exchange falling down because Bitcoin’s price was rising too fast. After the owner lost a lot of money, they decided to invest more in architecture and introduced a new feature to their APIs: limits to the client.</p><p>In the exchange, to guarantee a good performance, they send a new result every minute. If you request the same route several times in that same minute, you’ll get the same cached result. It’s a great way to ensure more performance and to decrease the chances of your server falling down. Of course, we have to study and analyze the business impacts by caching the response to every minute.</p><p>Also, using a layer to protect your service from DDoS attacks such as Cloudflare is a great option, and we can combine their solution with a good architecture on our APIs, This is actually what this exchange did, they combined a cached result with Cloudflare DDoS protection.</p><h3>6. Read the security section in the manual of your library</h3><p>Apparently, we are reading less and less, generation after generation. Also, we’re facing problems with paying attention for extended periods of time.. As a software engineer, I know that “patience”, “attention”, and “reading” are keywords in our daily routine.mSo it’s especially important that we discipline ourselves and read the documentation from our frameworks and third libraries, including the “Security Section”.</p><p>By using Express, I’ve noticed that we have a section called “Advanced Topics” and “Security Best Practices”.</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*-eNMd6LHYeKpFkQA" /></figure><p>This is awesome, but I know that most software engineers that have installed Express haven’t read the Express documentation, and probably, never bothered diving into the “Advanced Topics” section, much less the “Security Best Practices” page.</p><p>To my surprise, when I decided to implement Express in one of my APIs, I saw this section and found that Express offers wonderful documentation on how to protect your web service with Express. With that documentation, I was able to learn how to use Express in a way that did not compromise my system in the future.</p><h3>7. Don’t be paranoid and don’t neglect to study security</h3><p>After studying about security for my applications and web services, I started to go a little crazy! I couldn’t finish my tasks on time because I was thinking too much about all of the potential security breaches in my code. We have to remember that even big organizations like the CIA, Sony, eBay, Yahoo, JP Morgan Chase, Netshoes, Dropbox, YouTube and others, have been hacked. Considering that, don’t be so paranoid about your services, after all, if the hackers really want to hack your application, they probably will find a way. It’s just in their nature. The question is: how much time do you need to identify that a hacker bypassed your security barriers? With good logs and strong alerts strategy, we can identify breaches sooner and thus act on them quicker.</p><p>This is not an excuse to tell yourself that it’s pointless because hackers will win. Developers and Cyber security professionals work to build as many walls, mazes, traps and other defenses for hackers to become discouraged at and leave their system alone. So it’s best to make the hacker’s job as hard as possible in hopes that they move on to their next target.</p><p>Also, don’t neglect to study security. This post is covering the most basics security techniques that we should be learning in college or in beginner tutorials on the Internet. Most developers are not interested in protecting their services at a basic level. That’s a problem.</p><p>Therefore, don’t be paranoid but don’t neglect to study and invest time in protecting your applications. A good resource to study is the<a href="https://owasp.org/"> OWASP page</a>, especially the<a href="https://owasp.org/projects/"> projects page</a>. You can download the “Lab” projects to start them locally and hack them by yourself. These projects have security breaches implemented on purpose. It’s so funny to learn in this way, where you can be a hacker and the software engineer trying to stop the hacker (you) at the same moment. The Node.JS project to learn is called<a href="https://github.com/OWASP/NodeGoat"> NodeGoat</a> and there’s a<a href="http://nodegoat.herokuapp.com/tutorial"> tutorial guide</a> to help you to hack and protect a project. There are other projects in other languages as well, it’s worth taking a look at them.</p><p>The only way to truly find ways to stop a hacker is to think like one and break your own system. This is the fundamental idea of penetration testing</p><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/0*78f8sEwuRPDXghIM" /></figure><h3>8. Logs and Monitoring</h3><p>There are some situations where we need to audit our data to answer some kind of questions like: “Who edited this line?”, “What is making our server too slow?”, etc.</p><p>We can’t answer these questions if we don’t have good logs. That could be dangerous to any company, including if a company needs to identify a user with bad intentions. Imagine the following situation: Someone hacked your web service to process payments from the clients. Your boss asks: “How did the hacker pass through our security barriers?”</p><p>This could be a tough question if you don’t have good logs to start your investigation with. I doubt any executive is trying to hear the excuse that there weren’t any logs and therefore there is no way of knowing. That wouldn’t get you very far. So, don’t neglect your logs and make sure you have a system in place to keep track of them.</p><h3>Conclusion</h3><p>I hope this post helped introduce you to some basic steps to protect your web service and your web application. It’s important to start thinking about cybersecurity with our web applications and applying what we learn through research and practice to guarantee a safer system.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=36b11c3af36f" width="1" height="1" alt=""> ]]>
</content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>
<![CDATA[ Beyond Bitcoin: 5 Industries Successfully Applying Blockchain Technology ]]>
</title>
<link>https://medium.com/thecapital/beyond-bitcoin-5-industries-successfully-applying-blockchain-technology-603b30a94a7a?source=rss-e2a7c82d399b------2</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/603b30a94a7a</guid>
<category>
<![CDATA[ crypto ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ blockchain ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ cryptocurrency ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ security ]]>
</category>
<category>
<![CDATA[ bitcoin ]]>
</category>
<dc:creator>
<![CDATA[ Gabriel Ávila ]]>
</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 16:18:52 GMT</pubDate>
<atom:updated>2020-03-07T01:49:21.980Z</atom:updated>
<content:encoded>
<![CDATA[ <h4>By <a href="https://medium.com/u/e2a7c82d399b">Gabriel Ávila</a> on The Capital</h4><figure><img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*nu6C4atq3Tv0wWbOi5jlzA.jpeg" /></figure><p>Everyone has heard about the phenomenon that bitcoin and blockchain are, especially blockchain, which has a cryptographic and hash links as a foundation, keeping unalterable, permanent, and safety data.</p><p>I’m not here to speak about what blockchain is or how it works, let alone cryptocurrencies or the potential consequences with<a href="https://trio.dev/blog/what-can-we-expect-from-facebooks-globalcoin"> Facebook’s cryptocurrency launch</a>. I want to speak about some good applications of blockchain in the market, seeking to show how precious this technology is to us and potentially for small and mid-size companies.</p><h3>Financial Services and Fintechs</h3><p>Financial system solutions need to work with real money, and this can be challenging, mainly when we think about security. Blockchain offers a fast, safe, and permanent environment and sounds perfect for many financial organizations.</p><p><a href="https://www.itau.com.br/">Itaú</a>, <a href="https://www.santander.com.br/">Santander</a>, <a href="https://www.americanexpress.com/">America Express</a>, and even though <a href="https://www.transfergo.com/en">TransferGo</a>, are using <a href="https://www.ripple.com/ripplenet/">RippleNet</a>, the Ripple’s blockchain, to make global payments. Through this method, <a href="https://www.ripple.com/customer-case-study/reisebank/">RaiseBank exchanged 1,000 Canadian dollars into euros in Germany only in 8 seconds</a>. So much faster than the 2–6 business days it would typically take.</p><p>Seeing so many big players using blockchain promotes more confidence to other companies, for example, I’ve worked at the creation of a private and custom blockchain for a small company. They use this blockchain as a microservice to store, validate, and justify the whole balances as a way of avoiding frauds and hackers.</p><h3>Identification</h3><p>Blockchain is unalterable and permanent, and thinking about it some startups saw good opportunities as <a href="https://originalmy.com/">OriginalMy</a>. Their idea was to unify identities around the world on the blockchain.</p><p>Forget about national IDs, passports, and other documents or bureaucracies. In their app, you can register and pass through the “<em>Know Your Customer</em>” (KYC) compliance process. After their validation, they can prove that you are you in the blockchain.</p><p>Let’s imagine that you don’t need to register anymore on every website. To log-in, you just need to use your OriginalMy credentials (and if you want to apply this kind of login into your business, it’s already possible with their API). Do you need to sign a document? Don’t worry, just use your OriginalMy credentials, to sign any document. Are you at the airport and forgot your passport? It’s not a problem, maybe shortly, you will just show your OriginalMy credentials to board a flight.</p><h3>Education</h3><p>This new technology is changing every area of our lives, and education is not an exception. <a href="https://cointelegraph.com/news/malta-to-store-education-certificates-on-a-blockchain">Malta has announced</a> that educational certificates will be stored on the blockchain. <a href="https://cointelegraph.com/news/confirmed-sony-and-fujitsu-to-trial-blockchain-for-educational-record-integrity">Sony with Fujitsu has revealed</a> they will store course data, grades, student’s results, and certifications on the blockchain. In 2017, <a href="https://futurism.com/mit-has-started-issuing-diplomas-using-blockchain-technology">Massachusetts Institute of Technology has done the same</a>, issuing blockchain-based digital certificates to over 100 graduates as part of a pilot program in fall 2017.</p><h3>Health</h3><p>CVS Health Corp’s, Aetna, and a host of other health insurers as Anthem Inc, Health Care Service Corp <a href="https://www.coindesk.com/ibm-aetna-pnc-explore-medical-data-blockchain-for-100-million-health-plans">said in January</a> that they have partnered with IBM Corp to create a blockchain network aimed at cutting costs in the healthcare industry. The reason to use blockchain is the sharing of databases across a network of computers, for processing claims and payments, and to maintain directories with low costs and effectively.</p><h3>Smart Contracts and Decentralization</h3><p>In Ethereum blockchain, there is a mechanism called smart contract, which allows setting up a custom digital contract on the blockchain. You can create a custom smart contract coding with some languages and upload it to the blockchain network. Those contracts need to have terms and conditions that will execute when triggered.</p><p>For example, let’s imagine that, unfortunately, your father died, and you can have your inheritance in money. Who is responsible to make this transfer? Who can guarantee that transfer will happen?</p><p>With a smart contract, we can decentralize the responsibility to the blockchain network, where a term is triggered, and it will execute and make payment. We could be sure that the payment would be made while the internet exists. There is no company or person behind to ensure the inheritance, it is ensured by the blockchain.</p><h3>Other areas</h3><p>Sometimes we don’t see the limits of technology, mainly when it’s a new one. <a href="https://www.cryptokitties.co/">CryptoKitties</a> can show us how imagination can bring good services. Looking to the permanent and public aspect of blockchain they created virtual kitties. It’s great to think of the idea that your pet will never die and those pets do it.</p><p>In CryptoKitties you can collect and breed digital unique cats. Sounds kind of like joke, I know, but trust me, they can be worth a lot of money too. CryptoKitties launched November 28, 2017, and within its first week, collectors spent over <a href="https://medium.com/@galea/crypto-kitties-by-the-numbers-6d3bbd791aac">2 million dollars on the digital cats, with the highest price paid for a single kitten at $117,712</a>. It sounds like a joke, but it’s a serious and lucrative business.</p><h3>Is blockchain for you?</h3><p>I hope these examples explained that blockchain isn’t a distant technology designated only to big companies or financial proposes. For being something new, we can see how some misunderstand can difficult the identification of if your company really needs a blockchain application. To see if you need this kind of technology, ask yourself these questions below:</p><p>1- Does my service need to send global payments very fast with low costs?</p><p>2- Does my service need to make a public report as evidence?</p><p>3- Does my service need to execute a process with confidence?</p><p>4- Does my service need to protect extremely sensitive data from hackers or frauds?</p><p>5- Does my service need to process a lot of transactions and data very fast?</p><p>6- Does my service need to provide data even if my company doesn’t exist anymore?</p><p>Blockchain provides safety through permanent, unalterable public or private data with low costs and great performance. If your business needs to guarantee these key points, maybe you need a blockchain solution.</p><p>You can read this post on the <a href="https://trio.dev/blog/beyond-bitcoin-5-industries-successfully-applying-blockchain-technology-69675">Trio’s blog</a> as well.</p><p><a href="https://twitter.com/thecapital_io">JavaScript is not available.</a></p><iframe src="https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fupscri.be%2Ff%2F3c1144%3Fas_embed%3Dtrue&amp;dntp=1&amp;display_name=Upscribe&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fupscri.be%2F3c1144&amp;key=d04bfffea46d4aeda930ec88cc64b87c&amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;schema=upscri" width="800" height="400" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"><a href="https://medium.com/media/3b6b127891c5c8711ad105e61d6cc81f/href">https://medium.com/media/3b6b127891c5c8711ad105e61d6cc81f/href</a></iframe><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=603b30a94a7a" width="1" height="1" alt=""><hr><p><a href="https://medium.com/thecapital/beyond-bitcoin-5-industries-successfully-applying-blockchain-technology-603b30a94a7a">Beyond Bitcoin: 5 Industries Successfully Applying Blockchain Technology</a> was originally published in <a href="https://medium.com/thecapital">The Capital</a> on Medium, where people are continuing the conversation by highlighting and responding to this story.</p> ]]>
</content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>